[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
hello everyone this is priyanka raghavan
for software engineering radio and today
my guest is brian campbell
brian is a distinguished engineer at
ping identity where he's responsible for
a variety of products and designing them
like ping federate the open source jwt
library jose 4j
and mainly he's here on this show
because he's a co-author on you know
various ietf specifications and i just
went on the ietf spec and i was like
researching brian before the show and i
noticed that he's been a part of
specifications right from rfc 6755 which
was in 2012 to now which is 10 years
there are three latest rfcs on oauth 2.0
he also serves as an advisory board
member on identity verse and has talked
at various security conferences and
written blogs and talks on authorization
and identity extensively
and today we're mainly going to be
talking about
cryptographic defenses against stolen
tokens and i thought what better guest
than brian to have on the show so
welcome brian i'm really looking forward
to this chat
oh thank you priyanka i'm happy to be
here thanks for having me on is there
anything else you would like listeners
to know about you before we start the
show no i think you covered about
everything and probably more than i
really am so thanks for the kind intro
so let's just begin this journey one of
the things that we've done in software
engineering radios we've actually talked
a lot when i looked at the previous
episodes on identity but also on
authorization so we've done a show on
oauth 2 in 2019 with justin richard
where we mainly looked at the oauth 2 in
action i was done by one of the hosts
and they they really went into the
details of the oauth 2 different grant
types etc
and they just kind of peeked into these
defenses against stolen tokens
but increasingly in the news we're
seeing so many attacks
happening on stolen tokens and i thought
okay this would be a good show to
actually focus a little bit on how can
we defend against such type of attacks
so before we actually get there
one of the things i wanted to do is a
recap for our audience on in your own
words can you tell us what the author
protocol set out to do and the problem
it was trying to solve
sure or i can try it's actually sort of
a deceptively difficult question to
answer in any kind of synced or
meaningful way and as you pointed out
you did a whole show on it that goes in
the details but let me try
so oauth is an open ietf standard
authorization
protocol or really it's called a
framework because it is pretty
open-ended
and the main idea is it allows a user an
end user to grant access to their own
private resources stored on some site
to a third-party site or application
but it grants that access without having
to give up their username or password or
any of their own actual login
credentials to that third party those
resources usually are exposed via some
kind of http api
can be things like your calendar data
contacts lists the ability to read or
write your status updates on a social
site it could be bank account info
really whatever
and the
problem that oauth was primarily trying
to solve was enabling that kind of
access without
requiring users to share their passwords
across
different sites which is less of a
problem nowaday because of oauth but it
was increasingly becoming problematic at
the time that this started where you
were seeing
websites you know ask for your
gmail address and password so that they
could read your contact list which
that practice in itself is is one thing
but in order to do that you're basically
giving that third party site access to
your entire account to do whatever and
oauth comes along and tries to
make that sort of thing possible in a
more constrained way that delegates
limited rights to that client or
application and so what happens
is typically a client which is the oauth
term for the third party application
sends the user via a browser to the
authorization server which is another
oauth term
the authorization server is the
component that renders user interface
for that user through the web
and authenticates
if they're not already authenticated and
asks the user to approve the access that
that client application is is asking for
assuming that all goes well
the authorization server redirects
back to the client
including what's called an authorization
code which is just a little artifact
that the client turns around and
exchanges directly with the
authorization server to get back some
tokens typically an access token a
refresh token but these tokens that
represent then and are the credentials
for
making this limited access and the
client can then use the access token to
make api calls
at what's often called the protected
resource of the resource server but
that's the private resources that the
end user has granted access to oauth has
become and is a lot of other things as
well but that's sort of the main
canonical use case and flow and how it
works and the entities involved and
their names in the oauth parlance
great
another thing that you talked about is
the tokens right so if you talk to any
developer like a newbie developer who
comes and you ask me what's a that's jwt
token so could you just maybe explain
what's the difference between a jwt and
a bearer token
the same thing
they are the same thing and they're
different um in fact they they are
basically different classes of things so
comparing them like that is a bit of on
apples and oranges comparison
although jwt is a token format that was
developed in the same working group
in the ietf that developed oauth which i
think only further
compounds that confusion but jwt is a
token format it's a style of token that
contains the information
in whatever is meant to be conveyed in
the token usually
information about a user called claims
in json as a payload of a token that's
encoded and then typically signed
so it becomes a cryptographically
secured
token format
that is most often
a bearer token most often used as a
barotoken doesn't have to be but a
bearer token is more of a
concept or a classifier and not a format
itself a bear token is just any kind of
token
which can be used
without any further proof of anything
bearer meaning the holder of it a bear
token is any kind of token that you can
just show up and use
and that alone grants access or is
considered valid so they're related but
different as i said most
jwts as they're used in practice today
are in fact better tokens though they
don't have to be but bear tokens are a
broader class of things
in oauth the actual token format itself
is undefined so there's a lot of oauth
deployments
that pass around tokens that are just
sort of long random strings that serve
as a reference to
the actual data elsewhere
and those can be presented as bear
tokens as well either way it's just what
makes it a bearer is the act of
presenting it is all that's needed to
use it
one of the talks i listen to that you
gave it's called
the burden of proof and one of the
things that struck me in that and what
i'm thinking about is when you said the
bearer you can use the jwt anybody who
presents it the bearer can accept
different types of tokens and jwt is one
would it be similar to say a currency
yeah that's one of my favorite
references and certainly i didn't come
up with it but a bear token in a lot of
ways is equivalent to cash so if i have
a five dollar bill i can present that
and use it to buy services anywhere but
if you steal my five dollar bill it's
just as good to you as it was to me you
can use it to buy things at a store and
there's no additional checks
beyond simply holding that token to
consider it valid
and i think that probably plays into my
next question which is to kind of define
the replay attacks so i guess
that's
when it happens in that scenario that
you can just steal a token a bear a
token and then the attacks happen
yeah so whatever i have a hard time with
the word replay attacks just because i
think it's it's used by a lot of
different people in a lot of different
ways to mean different things
and i'm not sure i have my head wrapped
around one meaning that i really
can stick to but in general i think it
means the use the play the replay the
use of a bearer token by
some entity for whom it wasn't
originally intended and that could come
about from attacks on the oauth protocol
itself where there's been
issues with the way that the redirection
uris are validated that lead to token
leakage a whole variety of different
things like that that result in ways
that despite efforts to protect them
from leakage tokens do leak and do get
stolen
more recently you know there was news
around github and some of i don't know
the exact details but some third party
sort of automation tools integrating
with github had
tokens stolen from them i think they
were just stolen from storage at rest
but either way and and sometimes tokens
leak in
through log files or sort of despite our
best efforts they do sometimes leak out
and a replay attack then would be the
use of that token
after the fact and because they're
bearer as we've talked about whoever has
the token the thief then can use it as
though they are the legitimate holder of
it that's not the right word but there's
nothing preventing the
thief from using the token regardless of
how it was obtained
i think that i can clearly now
understand the
problem that we are trying to actually
look at but one of the things before i
dig deeper into this is
i did see that in blogs not only by you
but also by other security experts or
people in the ietf
they say the majority of times and you
know the popularity of oauth 2 is
because a bearer token is maybe enough
for most of the cases that you're doing
so can you just explain that a bit yeah
it's sort of a fine line and it's it's
almost a hard thing for me to say and
advocate for but we do hear about
attacks in the news things
happen there are problems with it but
you know what doesn't make the news is
the vast majority of stuff you do every
day online
is probably somehow protected by a
bearer token whether it's sort of
classical oauth which you probably use
online very much every day to just
regular old hp web sessions that are
granted to you after you authenticate
with the site
those are most certainly in in almost
all cases better tokens
just like a you know session cookies
usually only a bearer token most oauth
tokens are usually better
and there are many things in place
already that protect against their
leakage or their theft
and for the most part it works okay
it's not to say it's perfect but the
point is the vast majority of stuff we
already do
is based on bearer tokens and while
there are some problems there are some
leakages you know the the world hasn't
come crashing to an end and it supports
itself pretty well
for the majority of what we need to do
every day so
having something more than that is nice
it adds defense and depth but it's also
proven to be somewhat difficult so that
i think there's a combination of it's
pretty good almost good enough versus
the complexity of doing more
has kept us in a space where bear tokens
really are are kind of the mainstay and
in many ways that's okay it's usually
okay you know it's not preventing some
of us from trying to
facilitate more but it's not
an end of the world kind of scenario
it's a could be better kind of scenario
but in most cases it's probably all
right the reason i was asking for that
was also to talk a little bit about this
concept of a proof of possession maybe
you could talk to us about it because of
your long history with the ietf so it
appears that this is not something new
it's been there around for quite some
time for example if i looked at one of
these token binding
protocol version one i think it was
eight four seven one i saw that it's
been talked and also it was also talked
about in oauth 1. so maybe you could
just give us a brief history of this so
obviously all of all of you have been
discussing this for a long time and it's
not something new
so could you just walk us through that a
bit
yeah so proof of possession and
unfortunately it is often referred to by
different names but different people
usually meaning generally the same thing
but it sort of confuses the space and
confuses me anyway but proof of
possession generally means or describes
the idea that you're somehow
demonstrating
that a party that's sending a message
is in possession of some particular
cryptographic key
without
directly exposing that key
so it's really just
some kind of exchange or protocol that
shows that the
original message sender
possesses some
cryptographic key
and that in itself doesn't
do anything other than show possession
of that key
but what you have attempts in oauth and
other areas is to then
bind the issued tokens
to that key
so that
when
and then we we generally refer to those
as pop tokens or sender constraint
tokens or something like that but the
idea then being that there's something
in the token then
that says
i'm more than a bearer token in order to
accept me as good enough
you also have to ensure that whoever's
showing up with me proves possession of
this
associated key
and what that does is prevent the token
from being used by
someone who does not possess the key
and in turn you know prevents the kinds
of replay attacks assuming it's all
implemented and done correctly prevents
the kind of replay tax we've talked
about
unless the key too is somehow stolen but
typically keys are treated
more securely oftentimes even you know
in hardware non-exportable it's much
much less likely for those keys to leak
they're not sent over the wire
so the opportunity for that kind of
compromise is much lower than compromise
of the actual token itself and by
combining some proof of possession of
the key
with a binding of that key to the token
you're able to defend against not the
theft of tokens but of the use of the
tokens in some kind of malicious way
after the fact
and it all sounds nice but it turns out
that it's pretty difficult to do
reliably
and there have been a number of
different attempts to do something like
that as you mentioned oauth one
didn't
have exactly that in it but it had a
mechanism where it combined
a pseudo
sort of bespoke signature over to the
http request
with the token and a client held secret
which gave you something like
proof of possession of that client
secret that proved very very difficult
to implement correctly not so much
because of the signature itself but
because of the need to normalize the
input into the signature
trying to normalize http requests turns
out to be a really really difficult
problem that's hard to get right and so
there's lots of needly nitpicky kind of
interop problems around trying to do
those signatures
you've been a number of different ways
of attempts of doing it you mentioned
the token binding protocol which did
become an rfc there's a couple other
related rfcs that went with it
which
was sort of a novel and promising for a
while effort out of the iatf including
some very major players in the space
ironically not to actually bind tokens
but to provide a mechanism
for
proving possession
of a key pair
client generated key pair using both
tls and http
in a way that the use of this protocol
was negotiated in the tls handshake
and then a hb header was sent on every
request that included a signature
over the exported key material from the
tls layer which was a nice is a weird
violation of layers but a nice
tight binding between the two of them as
well and so basically you were proving
that the
client
possessed this key pair
over this tls connection and the
associated http requests on top of it
and then in turn the idea was that
applications at the next layer oauth for
example could bind
their tokens issued to
the token binding key pair provided by
the lower layers and there were many
people too that were envisioning binding
you know their session cookies to
those protections as well
and the way that it worked at the
different layers was sort of promising
because it was a it was a somewhat novel
approach to providing this and was based
on some work that google had done
previously around channel binding and
some other things
in their browser with some
experimentation
it was certainly an attempt to look at
it at least to provide the lower layer
of infrastructure for doing
proof of possession type of work but the
rfcs were published out of that working
group
but there were a number of things that
led to basically just
non-adoption of it and while they are
standards
they aren't actually widely available or
that's an overstatement they're really
not available in in practice today in
any platform or browser or really
anywhere so unfortunately one of those
sort of standards efforts that just
didn't take didn't take in a long run
and the world certainly littered with
with standards that didn't actually get
implemented and token binding
unfortunately i think was one of those
but it is demonstrative of the
difficulty in actually making this work
in a standardized
way for everyone and how difficult the
problem itself can be
and the efforts that have gone into it
trying to find some solution for it over
the long run
this is quite insightful actually and
one of the things i wanted to ask you
was mutual tls which we hear a lot in
the service mesh world how did that
inspire you to i mean i guess the group
to think about using this on top of
oauth 2 which is of course widely
popular maybe and just dial it back a
bit and maybe just give us one or two
lines on mtls and then why did you
decide to tie that in for this proof
yeah
let me try to do that so tls is i'm sure
most of your listeners know already is
the secure transport protocol that
underlies https and we use it all the
time and it's how
websites authenticate themselves to us
using a web browser so during the tls
handshake when the connection's set up
a bunch of cryptography goes on
including the presentation of a
certificate that says who the website is
and that's how we authenticate the sites
that we're talking to
that's sort of normal tls
the tls also provides an option for
the client to provide a certificate
during the handshake and
prove possession of the associated
private key so it's not just sending a
certificate it's sending a certificate
and signing bits of the handshake to
prove that it possesses the associated
private key so it's and typically then
used in a a manner to authenticate the
client but is also a proof of possession
mechanism for a public private key pair
as well
and there were
you know the long history of trying to
do some kind of proof of possession in
oauth and other related identity
protocols before that
fell in conjunction with a number of
regulatory
pushes
in various areas
largely but not exclusively coming out
of europe that were demanding that
big banks open up their services as open
or open-ish apis
to facilitate financial growth and
incentivize innovation around using
banking apis for fintechs and so forth
but coming out of a government
regulation basically saying
do open banking make bank apis available
and open
and as you probably know banks are
rather conservative in their security
posture and one of the desires was to
have a
legitimate proof of possession mechanism
for the presentation of oauth tokens to
those open banking apis it was all the
open banking not all most of it was
based around oauth
for the
issuance and consent and delivery of the
tokens but they also wanted more than
bear they wanted a proof of possession
mechanism there this is all happening
around the time that token binding
working group was working on this stuff
there was a lot of promise there and
folks were interested in it but it was
not mature
and ready to be used and despite all
the complexity of proof of possession
tls and mutual tls are actually a pretty
hard-won and long-standing
mechanism that exists today with
deployments that can interoperate that
does a proof of possession mechanism
and so it made sense sort of
pragmatically to try to
build a profile of oauth using mutual
tls
to achieve some level of proof of
possession as well as a higher level
assurance of doing client authentication
between the client and the authorization
server and then doing a binding of the
tokens to the certificate itself which
gives you the same proof of possession
properties and so forth so it for a long
time i i called the mutual tls oauth
work sort of a store brand version of
token binding because i envisioned token
binding as being kind of the cool
long-term new way to do it
didn't realize it wasn't going to
actually go anywhere but considered the
mutual tls stuff sort of like a a
short-term pragmatic interim solution to
provide for this
and maybe it'll have longer legs because
of the way things have happened but
we began work in the ietf oauth working
group to
specify exactly how
mutual tls could be used in conjunction
with oauth or layered on top of oauth to
achieve
bound tokens and client authentication
using well-known existing deployable
technologies today
and um you know it was ratified as an
rfc ratified's not the right word but i
i use it here and has been used and
deployed in a number of those
open banking type scenarios that i
described and more broadly as well so it
provides a workable solution today
interesting so the adoption rates are
pretty
good is that what you see
yes although it remains fairly niche
mutual tls is a technology that works
and is proven but is rather cumbersome
to
deploy and manage
and has
a lot of other drawbacks it's cumbersome
to say the least but its use in
conjunction with browsers is rather
fraught as well it has a pretty poor
user experience
and so it's often not at all used with
browsers so i guess that's to say it has
been
used there is deployment out there but
it's these niche deployments that really
had a strong need for this higher level
of security it solved the problem for
them but they're also the kinds of
places and institutions that can afford
the investment to manage this harder
more complicated more cumbersome
deployment of mtls
sure so what you're saying is that if
you were to use oauth to empty this in a
browser then it's probably the user
experience is not as smooth as what to
work we're used to
yeah it's worse than not as smooth to
the point where it's almost unusable so
unless you're in a i think a constrained
enterprise environment where
maybe the enterprise is provisioning
certificates out to your machine and and
all that's sort of taken care of of for
you
the user experience with mtls sort of on
the open web in a
random browser is just it's it's
prohibitively
difficult it presents the users with
selection screens around certificates
that are confusing and meaningless even
to people who
spend time with stuff and and kind of
know what it means and just really a
non-starter for kind of the average
user
it's just not a
viable solution for anything where the
oauth client itself is running
in the web browser or for that matter
for anything where the web browser
itself interfaces with and is asked to
provide a client certificate so you can
still use mutual tls in cases where
the sort of server to server componentry
is doing all that and the end user
interface stuff is presented via normal
hps but anytime you want to move the
the client authentication into the web
browser it's just really a non-starter
for most cases
i was going to ask you something else
but then something struck me now like
one of the things that we do with the
service to service call is we use this
thing called client credential flow
right you know what through so maybe is
this this place where the oauth 2 mtls
could come in for
when you're trying to do something
really secure like what you're saying is
banking transactions
yeah it's one option as you know there's
a lot of different grant types and ways
to obtain tokens in oauth but
client credentials being one where
there's not really a user involved it's
just one system
getting a token from the other system
and that's typically used where the
client system is a actual website so yes
it would be appropriate there for that
client website to use mutual tls
as its client credentials to
authenticate with the authorization
server and get a token issued for it
but you can also use mutual tls oauth
in the cases like the canonical case i
described before where the user's
bounced around through a browser
but the client itself is a website so
the browser presents a normal tls
connection to the end user
but the communication between the client
website and the authorization server
website and the resource server website
is all done mutual tls so anytime it's
server to server
mutual tls works okay it's when that
connection bleeds over into the web
browser that it becomes problematic from
an experience standpoint
so i wanted to ask you two things from
the spec when i looked at it it looked
like there are two flavors of client
authentication
one was you could use the regular pki
which we all know about
and then there was the self sign
certificate so maybe you could just
tell me a little bit about this
self-signed certificate and what is that
i mean it's just the thing that we
usually do that the client has the
self-signed certificate and then there's
a lot more work involved there or
instead of using ppa
the idea was to provide two different
ways of doing it to try to actually
accommodate different deployments and
actually maybe reduce some of the ease
not with the browser issues and
usability but with deployment and
management of a tls and pki
infrastructure so
with the pki-based approach of
authentication
you have your client configured or set
up in your authorization server and you
say something about its subject that you
expect to authenticate through mutual
tls
and then during the tls handshake the
certificate's validated up to a trusted
anchor
and then if the certificate contains
that particular subject in whatever form
then that's considered valid because you
both have who the subject is and that
this whole certificate chain was issued
by a trusted authority which works
that's kind of how we normally think
about tls and pki
but with the self-signed option we
wanted to give an option where the
certificate itself was really
just sort of wrapper metadata
unused data around a key
and a key pair
and rather than
setting up a name that you expect out of
the certificate to authenticate what you
do is configure that client with the
full certificate
and then during authentication
the mutual tls occurs and in order to
authenticate that client you then have
proof that they
possess the associated key and you just
make sure that it's the same certificate
that you've configured to be expected
from them
and by doing this you sort of provide an
alternative path of trust it's more like
just a out-of-band key exchange than
reliance on a
third-party
trust anchor pki being set up
and it can be
easier to deploy and manage because you
don't have to deal with the pki you're
just dealing with the exchange of
certificates more on like a pairwise
basis it's sort of like saying for this
you know this is the client's particular
secret but in this case this is the
client's particular key pair wrapped in
this self-signed certificate
so like in a deployment architecture
maybe where
these services are inside of trusted
virtual network or something
i could probably use this kind of a
scenario
where i don't need to get out
everything's within my network and so i
could use a self-signed certificate then
in the mtals world yeah but even in
an open deployment
the self-science certificate is
sufficient because the trust is
established
through
the registration of that certificate for
that particular client so it doesn't
have to be a closed environment to
facilitate it
it's just relying on a little bit of
different trust model and then you have
to things have to be set up such that
your servers will accept
any trust anchor they basically are told
to turn off validating the trust anchor
and so that what it does is it sort of
takes away the authentication piece from
the tls layer because there's no
chain walking or trust anchor validation
there and switches it over to really
just being a proof of possession
mechanism
of that key
during the handshake
and then oauth
layers on top of that and says okay
great you've proven possession of the
key is that in fact the key that i'm
supposed to get for this client if so
authenticate good if not
authenticate bad but it
moves or changes what it's getting from
the tls layer to just being about proof
of possession of the key and then the
key itself becomes the authentication
mechanism that's compared at the higher
level layer in oauth itself and then
maybe jump ahead of your next question i
don't know but regardless of which of
those is used the actual binding of the
issued access token
binds it to it takes a hash
of the certificate that was presented
regardless of whether
it was pki or self-signed base
and
associates a hash of the certificate
with the access token if it's a jwt it
includes that as a claim within the
token itself if it's a reference style
token
it's just stored server side and could
be retrieved via database lookup or
commonly through introspection which is
a way that oauth exposes
in a standardized base way for resource
servers to find out information
about validity and meta information
associated with the token it really ends
up just looking a lot like the json
payload of a jot but it's a different
way to obtain it and not in the token
itself so but either way the certificate
is sort of attached to the token by
binding the hash of that certificate to
the token itself
actually that was going to be my next
question just ask how does the jwt token
structure get modified so that's the way
you said that you include this
certificate and have a hash of that
in the jwt structure yeah and can you
also clarify the introspection column i
mean you're saying that so in case you
didn't want to do that then make do you
have the intro selection
yeah this is more sort of general base
oauth there's really
two main ways that token validation
and information
from the token is extracted for the
resources to use one is to include it
directly in the jwt
and the resource server validates that
and extracts the information from it
directly the other method that is
standardized in an rfc is to do what's
what's called introspection which is i
guess sort of a misleading name but
really all it is is a callback
is that the resource server receives
this token
and
makes a call to the authorization server
that says hey is this token valid and
can you tell me what's in it and the
response is a chunk of json that
that for all intents and purposes
is almost equivalent to what would be
the payload of a jot it's just a bunch
of json claims that say information
about
the token who the user might be the
client that's using it any
other data that that resource might be
needing based on configuration but so
either way with the certificate binding
there's a hash of the certificate
included in the token and it's either
obtained directly from the token or
through introspection but it looks the
same in the json
either way it's underneath a claim
that's called the cnf confirmation claim
cnn cnf short for confirmation
and then one
it's getting into some of the minutia of
all this but there's a it's a cnf with
something under it that's the x5 i can't
remember even it's the an indicator that
this is a hash of the x 509 certificate
and so
ultimately the resource either gets that
directly from the jot or through
introspection
and then it's expected to
compare
that certificate hash to the certificate
that was in turn presented to it during
a mutual tls connection from the client
on making the api calls and that's what
does the associated check for proof of
possession the mutual tls proves
possession of the key
and then the check of the hash proves
that this token was issued to the holder
of that key itself and there you get the
proof of possession check on the token
the other side of that being that if you
didn't have the tls key you couldn't
make
that connection and so if you try to
present that token without
that key or with a different key the
certificate hash check would fail and
you could reject that token
thus preventing
so-called replay by by asking for proof
of possession
using a lot of the same words over and
over again
to me it's now the story seems very
beautifully
complete like a circle
and just to kind of reiterate so one of
the things now i can see why it's
becoming expensive because now with
every one of these calls we would have
to do this check as well is that
something you'd like to talk about
the expensive part of the security i
think you've already addressed it
because that's the reason because it's
only in certain domains but is that when
i'm designing an api spec so should i be
looking at places where
there's more chance of data leakage or
something that i really need to protect
and that's where i would use the auth 2
mtls
so
the value of oauth 2 mtls is really
protecting against
the use of leaked or stolen tokens so
yes
whatever your api is
so subjective but if you consider it
high value if it's something that's
really important to protect against you
know malicious usage then something like
about mtls prevents
access
to that even if those individual tokens
are somehow leaked or stolen or whatever
and because of things like i said
earlier like banking is one area that
considers
fairly high value so that was an area
where it made sense to apply it
but there's certainly others and it's a
reasonable solution to
prevent against that kind of malicious
reuse of tokens no matter how they may
have leaked
from a cost standpoint i think the the
main cost comes in sort of
getting it up and running and
maintenance of the mutual tls
infrastructure itself it's just
it's just proven to be not
trivial over time and maybe someone will
come along and solve that but i'm not
aware of many people that have
in terms of a cost
transaction here at runtime
it's not
particularly more expensive because the
costly operations occurred during the
handshake that's where the proof of
possession of the keys is occurring
and the more expensive cryptographic
operations which are the public key
operations occur at the handshake
after that it's more or less just normal
tls
and while you do need to do the hash
check against the certificate on each
call that is itself relatively
inexpensive you just hash something and
compare hashes it needs to be constant
time and all that but it doesn't add
much cost overhead sort of on a marginal
case by case or transaction transaction
basis
the cost is really more in the overall
design and deployment and maintenance of
the system to the responsibility of the
validation sort of at the time of the
handshake and then yeah yeah
it's split but the expensive part of the
validation occurs at the handshake and
sort of the the secondary the cheap
check occurs
on the token validation where you're
just just comparing a hash to make sure
the certificate on the underlying
connection presented by the client
matches the one that the token was
issued to but that again is is
relatively inexpensive
that's a good segue into the next part
which i wanted to ask you a little bit
about the demonstrating proof of
possession of the application there the
depop which i didn't really do much
research on but i just wanted to ask you
about that what is that
yeah so it's yet another
attempt at defining a proof of
possession mechanism but it is one
that's on the track to becoming an rfc
within the ietf
and it was really born out of some of
the limitations and difficulties
around using mtls for this stuff as well
as
watching the the demise of the token
binding work where a lot of people had
placed their hopes and being able to use
that for applications in oauth with
those things sort of being unavailable
or too niche for deployment in a lot of
cases including within the browser
as we talked about before mtls doesn't
work very well there some of us got
together and
began working on a proof of possession
type approach
that could be done as the name implies
all at the application layer so rather
than relying on lower layers layers of
tls
it's using
signed artifacts passed around at the hp
layer and i don't know how much detail i
want to get into here but basically
with depop there's a mechanism where the
client
signs a jot
that
ultimately tries to prove possession of
a key pair similar to many of the things
we've talked about here but it does it
by signing a jot that is nominally
related to that specific http request so
there's a jot that includes the public
key it includes the uri to where the
http request was being sent some time
stamp information and some other things
to sort of show that it's it's fresh but
the end result is that the receiving
server can validate that
and have some reasonable level of
assurance that the client sending that
hp request
also possesses a private key
that the public key was referred to in
the request itself and then using that
which is it's just sent as an individual
distinct header surprisingly called
depop
because we're great with names
but that provides the
proof of possession mechanism which in
turn
oauth uses to bind tokens to the
associated key using very similar kinds
of constructs as the mutual tls stuff
but instead here it uses a hash of the
public key rather than the hash of the
certificate
and then on api type requests
the same header is sent in conjunction
with the access token so you get some
proof of possession of the key in that
header and you get then a token that's
bound to the key so there's the same
kind of check between the hash of the
key and the token to the key that was
presented itself which ultimately then
is a mechanism that prevents
that token from being used unless it's
also accompanied by this defop header
which in turns is showing that the
calling client
possesses the key and prevents misuse or
use of tokens by unauthorized parties in
in very much the same way
as the mutual tls stuff does but it does
it all sort of where the name derives
from at the application layer or at
least at the they should be application
and oauth application layer by using
these signed artifacts rather than
relying on the lower level layer of tls
and also then avoids
things like the
problematic user interface experience in
a browser with mutual tls it's it's much
more suited for that kind of deployment
because it doesn't run into those kinds
of issues that's very interesting and
also i can clarify the use as well
the other question i wanted to ask you
was also about these token revocations
right now anything changes there or is
that
because of using these protocols or
because i think anyway these are they're
not long-lived right they're typically
not long-lived all the issues of
token revocation versus length of token
lifetime how revocation might be
understood
it's really unchanged they remain
potential challenges in
in your deployment many people in fact
use introspection
that i was talking about before as a
mechanism to also check revocation
because when you have a jot token a jwt
it's all self-contained so there's
nothing indicating no way to know that
it has been revoked without doing some
other sort of something else
introspection gives you a way to check
back in with the authorization server to
find out if it's been revoked it's a
whole topic with trade-offs on its own
but the pop tokens don't change the
equation in any way you know there's
nothing additional
required to revoke them or to find out
that they've been revoked
i suppose
it only changes it a little bit in that
the need to revoke them may
be less because they're also bound to
these keys so you know a compromise of a
token
isn't as serious if they're pop or key
bound because
they can't be exploited because of that
binding so in many cases the need for
revocation i guess would be somewhat
somewhat reduced i don't know i don't
want to give license to not revoking at
all or to extremely long token lifetimes
but it does
present additional guards against the
reasons you might typically need to do
that
yeah i think that makes sense
yes just a little bit stumped by that
yeah i think that one of me that does
make sense i guess now that we've gone
through a lot of this i wanted to use
the last bit of the show to talk a
little bit about the future of oauth 2.
i do see a lot on something called
it's called grant negotiation and
authorization protocol called nap that's
how they pronounce it what is that is
that something that you could tell us is
that the
future of
oauth 2
i can tell you that i think they've
agreed on a pronunciation that has sort
of a g on the front of it so it's more
of a gnap
and you'd mentioned justin earlier
having talked about oauth
gnap is a work effort within the ietf
that is i think in many ways an attempt
to re-envision and redesign and rebuild
oauth
from the ground up and it's something
that justin's been heavily involved in
and pushing for
it is explicitly not
oauth
and the oauth
community for
whatever that is is continuing to work
on oauth as oauth and has stated that
good gnapp is not oauth 3
although it does
attempt to address many of the same kind
of problems so there's there's certainly
a relation there but it is i guess
independent effort
towards some of the same ends
that's
maybe clarifies it a little bit but yeah
it does try to do a lot of a lot of the
same stuff but almost think of it as a
ground-up rewrite of oauth which you
know depending on
your perspective may or may not be
necessary or the right use of time and
resources but that that's what it is
it's not really it's not oauth it's not
an evolution of oauth it's sort of
a new take on oauth from from the ground
up so the other thing i wanted to ask
you is also i was reading about this
thing called macaroon from google
macaron tokens
is that something you're familiar with
what is that is there a future in that
i'm
vaguely familiar with it so probably not
in a place to give you any real
authoritative answer but it's sort of a
different take on tokens as i understand
it and it allows i think what they call
caveats to be applied to a token by the
user which sort of constrain what it can
do
which it solves some similar problems to
key constrained or pop tokens but also
is very different
in that
you could like add a caveat before you
send a token which would
keep the receiver of that token from
turning around and
using it as its full power which is one
area that pop tokens also prevent that
kind of usage
but
the token itself is still uncaveated or
unrestricted
any more than originally was in
possession of that client so it's not as
effective as mitigating
the kinds of theft and replay attacks
from the client directly
i know there are some people that have
explored use of macarons in conjunction
with oauth i don't foresee a really
widespread acceptance and usage of that
but i could certainly be wrong
and they they do have their place they
get used in in other contexts but
they're subtly different enough
from the kinds of
problems that they solve and how they do
it that i i don't know that it's a easy
jump to sort of drop them in and use
them to solve these kinds of problems in
the oauth context and for that reason i
don't
i don't know that there's a large
feature there likely though elsewhere
it's it's an interesting technology that
provides some valuable
constructs but their applicability here
is is not quite
what's desired
another thing that i wanted to ask you
about the future is also
what two does differ from what one that
talked about
native clients
it acknowledged that but what is going
to happen in the future are we going to
like start going away from all these
redirects and is the protocol going to
change like that application there are
we just going to stop seeing
redirects because you're not going to be
only thinking about browsers and you
know as we go more native that's a great
question and i don't have the answer for
sure i will say that
a lot of native applications actually at
least these days
jumping between native applications
actually occurs through browser
redirects anyway
but still http and http redirects where
instead of running through the browser
the operating system is picking those up
and based on it's called claimed https
uris and or other i don't know the exact
names
rather than invoking that
http request invokes the handling of
that you know sends it to the local
application on that behalf so the the
constructs continue to use the same
mechanisms
i don't think it's going anywhere
anytime soon
but we are seeing pushes
from browsers to tighten up privacy
which may impact the kind of data that
is shared across redirects or can be
shared
we're seeing some
momentum behind different kinds of
ways to present credentials that may
localize it more in ways that don't
require redirects so
that's a lot of words to say i don't
really know
okay
fair enough this has been great i just
want to just sort of end with maybe some
advice for our listeners more than
advice maybe i could just say it's like
how do you see this whole journey evolve
in the future i mean oauth2 is there
anything that you see there's a definite
direction that you see people are
thinking about
stuff that might change or do you think
it's just going to be just improvements
over things which are already there
i tend to be sort of an incremental
improvement kind of person so i i would
lean
in that direction in general i will say
oauth to
you know for all its success and usage
it's a bit of a mess it can be
complicated hard to understand
there are some problematic things in it
and there's a
metric ton of different standards that
actually comprise oauth 2 and or sort of
its various extensions so
i think that's going to continue i think
they'll be continuing to be incremental
improvement work but there is some work
underway
in particular there's an effort around
defining oauth 2.1
which is
aimed at sort of consolidating some of
the many
specs that comprise oauth 2.0
adding or clarifying some best practices
removing deprecated or problematic
features particularly from a security
standpoint
so that's one area of active work that's
pretty incremental but i think very
pragmatic at trying to
clean up simplify and make more
accessible the stuff that we're we're
seeing now
but yeah i mean in general it's it a lot
too it's widely used it continues to be
you know pretty successful despite
problems i think that's typical of just
about any successful standard and at
least in the nearest term i think the
efforts we'll see will be continued sort
of
refinements and improvements around 2.1
and maybe extensions such as depop to
you know accommodate more niche or
higher value or different use cases but
nothing really revolutionary more
incremental type improvements going
forward that's perfect
this is great brian before i let you go
is there a place where people can reach
you would that be twitter or linkedin
i'm not great about any of that but i i
think you've finally tracked me down on
twitter right so that yeah that would be
uh probably the best place to track me
down i have the interesting handle with
a name like brian campbell it's hard to
get a unique handle in places but it's
two underscores
b
underscore c on twitter
i will definitely add that to the show
notes and thank you so much for
coming on the show and might i add that
i feel like i've learned a bit and i'm
thinking about apis or services that i
want to protect with the oauth 2 mtls
and i hope it's the same for our
listeners so thank you so much oh you're
you're more than welcome thanks for
having me on and i do hope it's been
somewhat informative and not too
too boring or too much minutiae it's
hard we get into the weeds with some of
this stuff
i appreciate you saying that yeah this
is great thank you and this is priyanka
raghavan for software engineering radio
thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of sc radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening